Yesterday, Chinese company Alibaba
dropped a brand new openweight long
horizon mixture of experts agent coding
model named Quen 3 coder. And amazingly,
it's the first openweight model that
matches the programming performance of
Claude 4, the undisputed leader of AI
vibe coding tools at the present time.
Not only is the Quen 3 coder model open,
but they also just released a brand new
CLI tool forked from the recently open
source Gemini CLI that can take
advantage of all the models agentic
properties like the ability to run,
execute, and test your code from the
command line. That's terrifying news for
any programmer still left with a job,
but mathematicians are also on life
support right now because both Google
and OpenAI just achieved gold medals in
the International Mathematical Olympiad.
In today's video, we'll take a look at
the latest AI breakthroughs and find out
if Quen 3 coder can actually compete
with Claude 4. It is July 23rd, 2025,
and you're watching the code report.
Just last week, the open model scene got
a big upgrade with the Chinese Kimmy K2,
but now Quen 3 coder pushes things even
further. The model was trained on 7.5
trillion tokens with a 70% code ratio.
In other words, it's seen a billion
times more code than the average
developer with 50 years of experience.
They even use their previous model to
clean up noisy training data, the highly
meta process where AI basically
determines which data to use to train
itself. When it comes to the training
process, they use something called long
horizon reinforcement learning across
20,000 parallel environments. The model
actually tries to solve real world
problems in real environments where it's
executing and testing code. You can
think of Quen's training infrastructure
like a coding boot camp with 20,000
graduates all working on the same
problem simultaneously, except they
never get tired, never argue, and never
ask, "Is this a breaking change?" And
the end result speaks for itself in
these benchmarks. Based on this
benchmark, Quen is outperforming Kimmy
and GPT4.1 and almost on par with Claude
4, but doing so with a much smaller
model size, which is important because
the bigger the model, the more
electricity and GPUs you need to run it.
What's also really impressive about Quen
3 coder is that it has a 256,000 token
context window that can stretch up to 1
million tokens. For reference, that's
enough to hold the entire codebase of
most startups and all of their technical
debt. Quen 3 coder is an openweight
model, but if you think you're going to
run it locally on your laptop, it's time
for a reality check. To harness the full
girth of the 480 billion parameter
version, you would need tens of
thousands, if not hundreds of thousands
of dollars worth of GPUs along with a
large wallet to pay the electricity
bill. Realistically, to try it, you'd
want to get an API key from a cloud
provider, then hook it up to the new
Quen CLI tool, which again is a fork of
the Gemini CLI. Overall, this does
appear to be a big leap forward for open
coding models. But I doubt that it will
make much of a dent in Claude's
dominance in the coding world. To be
Claude, a company needs to release a
model that's not only open and
inexpensive, but that surpasses Claude's
capabilities by a significant margin.
Like OpenAI was recently supposed to
release its own Open model, but that's
been delayed with the rumor for the
delay being that these Chinese models
would absolutely crush it. That's just
one of many L's taken by OpenAI
recently, like Zuck gutting all of their
talent. But OpenAI did get a big win a
few days ago when they achieved a gold
medal in the International Mathematical
Olympiad. What's funny though is that
they made a dick move by announcing this
before the closing ceremonies of the
event in order to overshadow Google and
the press, who also achieved gold medal
level performance. However, that ended
up backfiring because it just made
OpenAI look desperate. But if you want
to write really good code with AI, you
need to check out Code Rabbit, the
sponsor of today's video. Their free VS
Code extension gives you advanced code
reviews right in your editor. And their
new fix all with AI feature passes all
of Code Rabbit's review context directly
to the AI code agent of your choice is
so it can make all the changes for you.
This saves you from needing to click on
each review comment yourself, giving you
more time to write even more broken code
like a true artisan. Code Rabbit is free
to use in the IDE and works seamlessly
with VS Code and forks like Cursor and
Windsurf. Download it for free with the
link below to try it out. This has been
the code Report. Thanks for watching and
I will see you in the next one.